Guide to the Paul Baerwald Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Paul Baerwald Papers,
1857-1961
[Bulk: 1907-1950].
Baerwald, Paul, 1871-1961.
1.69 linear ft (4 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book an Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0059
4078513
This collection documents the life of Paul Baerwald, a banker and philanthropist who served as chairman of the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee from 1932-1961. It also includes materials by and about Baerwald's father, Hermann Baerwald, a German educator and historian.
Biographical Note
Paul Baerwald was born in 1871 in Frankfurt, Germany. His father, Hermann Baerwald, was director of the Philanthropin, a Jewish high school in Frankfurt, for 31 years. Baerwald left Germany at nineteen to join the investment firm Speyer & Brothers in London, and in 1895 he was sent to work in New York City. Baerwald became a partner at Lazard Freres in 1907. He met Edith Jacobi in New York, and they were married in 1909. The couple would have four children, Pauline, Jane, Florence, and Herman.
In 1914, Paul Baerwald helped found the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee (JDC), an international relief organization that provides help to Jews suffering as a result of poverty, persecution, natural disaster, or war. He retired from Lazard Freres in 1930 to devote his full attention to philanthropic work, and would serve with the JDC for 45 years, first as treasurer, and then as chairman in 1932 and honorary chairman from 1945 until his death. In 1949, JDC opened a school in Versailles, France, to train social workers. The school was transferred to Hebrew University in Jerusalem in 1958 and was named the Paul Baerwald School of Social Work in his honor.
In addition to his extensive work with JDC, Baerwald served on President Franklin Roosevelt's Advisory Committee on Political Refugees during World War II. He was a close friend of New York governor and senator Herbert H. Lehman, and they collaborated on JDC projects as well as other public and philanthropic works. Baerwald was also a trustee and founder of the New York Foundation; trustee of the Palestine Economic Corporation; treasurer of the Wollman Foundation; and trustee and treasurer of the Soloman and Better Loeb Convalescent Home.
Paul Baerwald died in New York on July 2, 1961.
Scope and Content
This collection documents the work of Paul Baerwald, particularly in his capacity as chairman of the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee from 1932 to 1961. It also holds material by and about Baerwald's father, Hermann Baerwald (1828-1907) a German historian and director of the Philanthropin, a Jewish high school in Frankfurt, Germany. Materials include correspondence, photographs, speeches, reports, and clippings.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into three series:
Series I: General, 1916-1961
Series II: Correspondence, 1924-1961
Series III: Hermann Baerwald, 1857-1960
Subseries III.1: Published Works and Manuscripts, 1857-1960
Subseries III.2: Published Works about Hermann Baerwald, 1893-1951
Subjects
American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee.; Herbert H. Lehman Collections (Columbia University).; Philanthropin (Frankfurt am Main, Germany).; Bet ha-sefer la-'avodah sotsyalit 'a. sh. Pa'ul Berṿald.; Baerwald, Hermann, 1828-1907.; Baerwald, Paul, 1871-1961.; Educators--Germany.; Historians--Germany.; Jews--Charities.; International relief.; Refugees.; Social service.; Photographs
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1968 M-40 Faulk, Mrs. Myron S., Jr. Gift
Gift of Mrs. Myron S. Faulk, Jr., daughter of Paul Baerwald, in 1968.
PDF available.
- Series I: General, 1916-1961
  This series contains a variety of materials, including biographical information, letters from Baerwald to his children and extended family, business papers, and drafts of speeches given at conferences and meetings.
  - Autobiographical and Biographical Papers, 1952-1954 (contains photographs) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Business/Career--Memoirs and Papers, 1916-1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters to His Children, 1941-1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda, Articles, and Correspondence, 1920-1961, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 4 to 5)
  - Speeches, 1932-1959, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 6 to 10)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1924-1961
  This series holds a small amount of personal and business correspondence, as well as associated reports, articles, and pamphlets. Some files contain letters from prominent individuals such as Albert Einstein, Herbert Lehman, and John D. Rockefeller, while others concern organizations and committees Baerwald worked closely with. Many of the conversations relate to the JDC. There are also several files on the Baerwald School of Social Work, which include photographs taken at the school's original building in France and biographies of some of the first students. The series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Brandeis, Louis D., 1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1940-1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Coolidge, Calvin, 1927-1931 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Einstein, Albert, 1933-1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Forrestal, James, 1944-1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Hebrew Union College, 1941-1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Jewish Theological Seminary, 1942-1951 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Johns Hopkins University, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Joint Distribution Committee, 1927-1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Lazard Freres, 1927-1949 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Lehman, Herbert H., 1933-1946 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Lehman, Herbert H., 1933 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Lincoln School--Teachers College, at Columbia University, 1924-1929 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - London, Fritz, 1946-1954 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - New York Foundation, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Paul Baerwald School of Social Work (Folder 17)
    - General, 1950-1951 April (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - General, 1950 February-1951 March (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - General, 1948 October-1949 December (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - ROBO, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Klein, Philip, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Israel, 1950-161 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - President's Advisory Committee on Political Refugees, 1936-1959 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Rockefeller, Dr. John. D, 1926-1937 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1938-1945 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Roosevelt Committee to Check the Reorganization of the Bank of the United States, 1931-1932 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Selective Service Committee, New York City, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Shotwell, James T., 1927 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Taylor, Myron C., 1938-1953 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Warburg, Edward M. M., 1939-1948 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Warburg, Max M., 1940-1946 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Watson, Thomas J., 1938 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Weizmann, Chaim, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Welles, Sumner, 1939-1943 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - William J. Wollman Foundation, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - William J. Wollman Foundation, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Young, Owen, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Series III: Hermann Baerwald Papers, 1857-1960
  Files in this series relate to Paul Baerwald's father, Hermann Baerwald, and pertain mainly to education in Jewish communities.
  - Subseries III.1: Published Works and Manuscripts, 1857-1960
    This subseries holds published articles, drafts, and notes by Hermann Baerwald. Most are about education and the history of the Philanthropin high school in Frankfurt, Germany, and are written in German. There is also a small amount of correspondence and a file of family papers.
    - Biographical, Autographical, and Assorted Family Papers, 1926-1955 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Papers and Correspondence, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Assorted Writings, 1858-1960 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "Historische Miszellen…"--Photostats, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "Zur Geschichte der Schule--Erster Teil: Das Philanthropin, 1804-1913," 1869 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "Zur Geschichte der Schule--Zweiter Teil, 1804-1812," 1875 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "Der Alt Freidhof der israelitischen Gemeinde ze Frankfurt a.M.," 1883 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Leopold Ranke, 1857-1885 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Subseries III.2: Published Works About Herman Baerwald, 1893-1951
    This subseries contains articles about Hermann Baerwald's life and work, including articles on his years as a school director, a bibliography, memorial speeches, and biographical clippings.
    - Manheimer, Adolf--"Festspiel zu Ehren des Direktors der Realschule der Israelitischen," 1893 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Dobriner, Hermann--"Abschiedsfeier fur den Direktor Hernn Dr. Baerwald," 1900 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Adler, S.--"Zur Erinnerung der Realschule der Israel," 1907 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Adler, S.--"In Memoriam Dr. Hermann Baerwald…" 1907 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Adler, S.--"Direktor Dr. Hermann Baerwald," 1907 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Baerwald, Paul, ed.--"Dr. Hermann Baerwald, 1828-1907," 1950 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Baerwald, Paul, ed.--"Dr. Hermann Baerwald, 1828-1907" Reviews, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Kisch, Guido--"Bibliography of Publications by and on Hermann Baerwald, 1828-1907," 1950 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Articles about Hermann Baerwald, 1907-1951 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Photograph, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)